{"tossups": [{"question": "In Strasbourg in 1988, this leader proposed a non-nuclear \u201czone of peace\u201d that banned Chinese immigration to his homeland. This winner of the 1989 Nobel Peace Prize currently lives in Dharamshala, India, having fled after a 1959 uprising was put down by the Chinese. This man was chosen as the 14th to hold his position at the age of 2 as the reincarnation of Thubten Gyatso. For ten points, name this exiled religious figure, the leader of Tibetan Buddhism.", "answer": "the 14th<b> Dalai Lama</b> (or Jetsun Jamphel Ngawang Lobsang Yeshe<b> Tenzin Gyatso</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man and Mario Amaya were shot by the author of the SCUM Manifesto in 1968. This man\u2019s creation of 15 images of a totaled car sold for $105 million in 2013. This artist of<em> Silver Car Crash</em> directed a film of the Empire State Building over the course of six hours and made numerous silkscreen images of bottles of Coca-Cola, Campbell soup cans, and other consumer goods. The Factory was the primary studio of, for ten points, what American pop artist?", "answer": "Andy<b> Warhol</b> (or Andrew<b> Warhola</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "PETA has protested a ritual held one day before this holiday in which a chicken is swung over the head, then donated to charity. The Ne\u00b4\u0131lah is read on this day, the tenth of Tishrei, which includes five prayer services and fasting. In 1973, this holiday was marred by a surprise attack in the Sinai Peninsula by Egypt against Israel. For ten points, name this Jewish Day of Atonement, the holiest day of the Jewish year.", "answer": "<b> Yom Kippur</b> (or<b> Day of Atonement</b> before mention)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "A rebellion against Ottoman incursions into this modern-day country in the late 1400s was led by the nobleman Skanderbeg. An Italian invasion during the buildup to World War II ended monarchical rule in this nation under King Zog, and this Southeast European country was ruled for much of the Cold War by the Communist regime of Enver Hoxha [HAW-ja]. For ten points, name this Balkan nation whose capital is Tirana.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Albania</b> (or Republika e<b> Shqiperise</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This author wrote the short stories \u201cThe Sing-Song of Old Man Kangaroo\u201d and \u201cHow the Leopard got His Spots.\u201d The title character of one of this man\u2019s works is used as a pawn in the \u201cGreat Game\u201dbetween Russia and Britain, and a poem by this man encourages a certain group of people to \u201csend for the best ye breed\u201d. For ten points, name this Victorian author of \u201cThe White Man\u2019s Burden,\u201d<em> Kim</em>, and <em>Just-So Stories</em>.", "answer": "Rudyard<b> Kipling</b> (or Joseph Rudyard<b> Kipling</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "This president tried to send John Slidell to negotiate the purchase of territory in modern New Mexico. He sent Nicholas Trist to negotiate a treaty that replaced the Nueces River with the Rio Grande as a national border and ended the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this \u201cdark horse\u201d president during whose term the United States gained territory in present-day California.", "answer": "James K.<b> Polk</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man claimed to feel \u201cnothing\u201d after returning from exile following the White Revolution. In one speech, he referred to the United States as the \u201cwounded snake\u201d and the \u201cGreat Satan.\u201d This leader\u2019s objections to the novel<em> The Satanic Verses</em> led him to issue a fatwa against author Salman Rushdie. For ten points, name this Shia Islamic cleric who replaced Reza Pahlavi in the 1979 Iranian Revolution.", "answer": "Ayatollah<b> Khomeini</b> (accept Ruhollah<b> Khomeini</b>; accept Imam<b> Khomeini</b>; prompt on <b>Ayatollah</b>) <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The perioikoi were a class of freed people living in this city, and the mothakes were raised as citizens of this city. This city\u2019s navy, led by Peisander, was destroyed at the Battle of Cnidus, part of the Corinthian War that this city fought alongside the Peloponnesian League. The Agiad and Eurypontid lines ruled this city, whose legendary founder and lawgiver was Lycurgus. For ten points, name this militaristic Greek city-state, the long-time rival to Athens.", "answer": "<b> Sparta</b> (accept<b> Lacedaemon</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "In this show\u2019s third season, an Aqua Net design showing four people riding in a convertible has to be remade following the John F. Kennedy assassination. This show\u2019s protagonist assumes his commanding officer\u2019s identity during the Korean War, and discusses the meaning of nostalgia while delivering a sales pitch for the Kodak Carousel slide projector. For ten points, name this recently-ended AMC drama starring Jon Hamm as 1960s advertising executive Don Draper.", "answer": "<b> Mad Men</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One leader of this group reportedly lost his right eye at the Battle of Arghandab in 1987 and died of tuberculosis in 2013. This group did not announce that leader\u2019s death until 2015 and is disputing reports that his replacement, Akhtar Mansoor, was killed in December 2015. Mullah Muhammad Omar led this organization and was President of its home country until 2001\u2019s Operation Enduring Freedom. For ten points, name this Islamic insurgent group that once controlled Afghanistan.", "answer": "<b> Taliban</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This Supreme Court justice typically votes with Scalia, Thomas, and Alito to uphold conservative rulings.", "answer": "John G.<b> Roberts</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A coin struck in this city with a fleur de lis on one side and John the Baptist on the other became the most popular coin for transactions in Europe in the 14th century. The castato system was instituted in this city after a successful war against the Visconti of Milan, and this city was ruled by Piero the Unfortunate before being taken over by a Dominican friar in 1494. For ten points, name this Italian city, ruled for a brief time by Girolamo Savonarola and home to the Medici family.", "answer": "<b> Florence</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>John Dickinson, the author of</b><em><b> Letters from a Pennsylvania Farmer</b></em><b>, refused to sign this document. Charles Thomson presided over the meeting that produced this document,</b> <b>and sent its final, handwritten copy to John Dunlap for (+)</b> <b>printing. Richard Henry Lee</b> <b>introduced the resolution creating this document, and Roger Sherman and Benjamin (*) </b>Franklin served on the Committee of Five that edited this text. For ten points, name this document whose Preamble asserts that \u201cWe hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal,\u201dwritten by Thomas Jefferson.", "answer": "<b> Declaration of Independence</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>William Cosby was the target of one man who made his fortune through the sale of these entities. An account titled \u201cHeed Their Rising Voices\u201d was published by one organization that created these entities and led to a (+) lawsuit that established the standard of \u201cactual malice\u201d with regards to libel. John (*)</b> Peter Zenger, a printer of these documents, was acquitted in a case that established truth as a defense against libel. For ten points, name these periodicals, the subject of the court case<em> New York Times v. Sullivan</em>.", "answer": "<b> newspaper</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader allowed for the publishing of Alexander Solzhenitsyn\u2019s</b><em><b> One Day in the Life </b><b>of Ivan Denisovich</b></em><b> and he attempted to increase agricultural production by starting the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Virgin Lands Campaign. This leader reportedly banged his shoe on a table during a</b> <b>U.N. Conference and 4 years earlier had told Western diplomats \u201cwe will (*)</b> bury you!\u201d He complained about his predecessor\u2019s personality cult in the \u201cSecret Speech\u201d and was replaced in his highest position by Leonid Brezhnev. For ten points, name this Soviet leader during the Cuban Missile Crisis.", "answer": "Nikita<b> Khrushchev</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s oldest neighborhood, just east of Storyville, features buildings</b> <b>with distinctive (+)</b> <b>ironwork galleries and balconies. Another neighborhood in this city,</b> <b>which lies downriver of the Industrial Canal, suffered (*)</b> catastrophic damage in a 2005 storm that breached the levees of the Mississippi River. The Lower Ninth Ward and the French Quarter are in, for ten points, what Louisiana city?", "answer": "<b> New Orleans</b>, Louisiana", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Victor Espinoza and Bob Baffert\u2019s work with this athlete resulted in a runner-up finish</b> <b>at Saratoga and nine victories.</b><em><b> Sports Illustrated</b></em><b> was criticized for naming (+)</b> <b>Serena</b> <b>Williams its 2015 Sportsman of the Year over this athlete, who completed a Grand Slam with his (*)</b> Breeders\u2019 Cup victory. For ten points, name this horse who won the Belmont, Preakness, and Kentucky Derby to complete horse racing\u2019s first Triple Crown since 1978.", "answer": "<b> American Pharoah</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>Rexford Tugwell served as this territory\u2019s governor during World War II, shortly before two of its nationalists killed policeman Leslie Coffelt in an attempt to assassinate Harry (+) Truman. Its current governor, Alejandro Garcia Padilla, believes that it would turn into a\u201cLatin American ghetto\u201d if the (*)</b> statehood movement were to succeed. For ten points, name this U.S. Commonwealth with capital San Juan, where 834,000 citizens voted support for making it the 51st U.S. state in 2012.", "answer": "<b> Puerto Rico</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>Eight decades after this war, Hyman Rickover led a commission refuting the</b> <b>Eight decades after this war, Hyman Rickover led a commission refuting the</b> <b>initial claim behind this war. Thomas Brackett Reed resigned as (+)</b> <b>initial claim behind this war. Thomas Brackett Reed resigned as (+)</b> <b>Speaker of the</b> <b>House due to his opposition to this war. Public support for this war was fueled by</b> <b>the leaking of the (*)</b> DeLome Letter and William Randolph Hearst\u2019s \u201cyellow journalism\u201d. For ten points, name this 1898 war in which the United States gained Cuba and the Philippines from a European nation. ANSWER:<b> Spanish-American</b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}